Guide to the Djibril Tamsir Niane Audiorecordings Documenting Guinean Oral Traditions
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Djibril Tamsir Niane audiorecordings documenting Guinean oral traditions
1960-1980
MS 1935
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.75
(63 audiotapes)
The Djibril Tamsir Niane audiorecordings comprise an oral history of Guinea. The recordings (reel-to-reel audiotapes) were made by noted Guinean scholar Djibril Tamsir Niane, primarily from 1969 to 1971. Included in the collection are field recordings of interviews, oral histories, epic tradition and musical performances, and ceremonies of several ethnic groups, particularly the Baga and Maninka, in several languages. The recordings are the only significant body of audio historical data on Guinean indigenous history and culture collected between 1958, when Guinea gained independence from France, and Sékou Touré's death in 1984. Also included in the collection are a few recordings of radio broadcasts.
Niane, Djibril Tamsir, 1932-
General
This collection was digitized through the generous support of the Arcadia Foundation.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection is available in digital form through the Yale University Library
Biographical / Historical
Djibril Tamsir Niane (II) was born in Conakry, Guinea, in 1932. He is a noted Guinean scholar historian, editor, dramatist and author of Epopée de Soundiata (1960, published in English as Sundiata: An Epic of Old Mali in 1965). He published widely on West African oral tradition and West African history. His early career spanned the tumultuous years of Sékou Touré's regime in Guinea. From 1961 to 1964 he was imprisoned for his activities as a member of the teachers' union. He was released to take part in a Polish-Guinean archeological expedition, on which he worked until 1967. In 1968, Niane became dean of the Faculty of Social Sciences at the University of Conakry. While there, he conducted ethnographic research on Guinean oral traditions. In Guinea-Conakry from 1969 to 1971, Professor Niane conducted research while the Sékou Touré regime's "demystification program" focused on the destruction of all traditional cultural elements, actively discouraging academic interest in such subjects. At considerable personal risk, Niane and a team of his university students investigated Baga culture in their coastal villages, as well as collecting oral history and tradition elsewhere in Guinea. Fearing further political persecution, Niane left Guinea in 1972. He escaped to Dakar, Senegal, where he and his family remained in exile until the death of Touré in 1984. In addition to his scholarly career, Niane held several ministerial and cultural posts while in Dakar and was a member of the comité de pilotage in Guinea.
Sources: Conrad, David C. "Bold Research During Troubled Times in Guinea: The Story of the Djibril Tamsir Niane Tape Archive," History of Africa 37 ( 2010), 355-378, and "Djibril Tamsir Niane," in Henry L. Gates Jr., and Emmanuel Akyeampong (eds.), Dictionary of African Biography (Oxford, in press).
Scope and Contents
The Djibril Tamsir Niane audiorecordings comprise an oral history of Guinea. The recordings (63 reel-to-reel audiotapes) were made by noted Guinean scholar Djibril Tamsir Niane, primarily from 1969 to 1971. Included in the collection are field recordings of interviews, oral histories, epic tradition and musical performances, and ceremonies of several ethnic groups, particularly the Baga and Maninka, in several languages. The recordings are the only significant body of audio historical data on Guinean indigenous history and culture collected between 1958, when Guinea gained independence from France, and Sékou Touré's death in 1984. Also included in the collection are a few recordings of radio broadcasts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Djibril Tamsir Niane, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection is digitized. Researchers must use the digital copies instead of the originals.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The tapes are arranged by tape number assigned by the repository.
Legends -- Africa -- Mali; Mandingo (African people) -- History; Mandingo (African people) -- Kings and rulers; Oral tradition -- Africa; Tales -- Guinea; Guinea -- History; Guinea; Mali (Empire); Audiotapes; Keita, Soundiata, -1255; Niane, Djibril Tamsir, 1932-
- Un vétéran de Lam Djoulbe II, recorded at Ségou, Circa 1966, 1970-1979; Tape 1; 1 (Box 1)
  Summary (English)
  Track A: Part 1 of an Interview in Ségou, Mali with a Veteran of Sekou Amadou's Campaign to Sokoto (1966). Apparently recorded over an earlier track, indecipherable in its present condition, continued on Tape 28, Tracks A and B.
  Track B: Superficial discussion in Wolof, French and Peul languages.
  Summary (French)
  Track A: Apparemment l'enregistrement couvre un ancien morceau, indéchiffrable dans les conditions actuelles, et continue sur Tape 28, Tracks A and B.
  Track B: Discussion superficielle en wolof, français et peul.
  - Preservation Masters, 2
  - Digital Copies, 2
- Al-Haj 'Umar, Circa 1970-1979; Tape 2; 1 (Box 2)
  Track A: A Song of the Serer people of Senegal but sung in Wolof. Music guitar and kora, male vocalist leads with responses by female vocalist.
  Track B: A Multilingual West African Love Song. Beautiful female voice sings in Maninka, Susu and Wolof.
  Track C: [blank track]
  Track D: [blank track]
  Track E: Military Guards' Coercion of a Dictator's Audience. French language skit in Dakar, Guinean soldiers argue and complain about their duty of forcing citizens to act joyful during a speech by President Sékou Touré.
  Track A: Musique à la guitare et à la kora, une voix masculine mène le chant et une voix féminine lui répond.
  Track B: Une belle voie féminine chante en malinké, susu et wolof.
  Track E: Un sketch de langue française à Dakar, des soldats guinéens discutent et se plaignent de devoir forcer les citoyens à être joyeux pendant un discours par Sékou Touré.
  - Preservation Masters, 5
  - Digital Copies, 5
- Histoire de Samori et Séré Bréma, Circa 1969-1970; Tape 3; 1 (Box 3)
  Track A: Epic of Almami Samori Touré Samori. Maninka language narrative, possibly by Babu Condé, with kora music, continues on Tape 30, Track A.
  Track B: French popular music. Charles Aznavour and others.
  Track A: Récit en malinké, par Babu Condé, avec musique à la kora.
  Track B: Charles Aznavour et autres.
  - Digital Copies, 2
- "Yamudu - SARA Keme Burema Tara", Circa 1970; Tape 4; 1 (Box 4)
  Track A: Susu language Interviews on the History & Culture of Baga Villages: Sobané and Sibòti, and a Fulani language interview on Futa Jalon. 1. Abou Sylla on early settlers and descent from Kanfori Bangoura; Atlantic slave trade; conflict with Fulani 2. Fulani informant, Arabic blessing; Muslim leaders of the Fouta Jalon including Alpha Yaya Diallo; Fulani coastal slave raids.
  Track A: 1. Abou Sylla parle des anciens habitants et des descendants de Kanfori Bangoura; de la traite des esclaves; du conflit avec les Peuls; 2. L'informateur peul fait les bénédictions en Arabe; les notables musulmans du Fouta Djalon incluant Alpha Yaya Diallo; les raids peul d'esclaves sur les côtes.
- L'histoire des Maninka par Mamoudou (?), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 5; 1 (Box 5)
  Track A: Sunjata fasa Part 1, by Kèlè Monson Diabaté of Kita, Mali. History of the dispersion of the Mande people, continued, Tape 10, Track A.
  Track A: Histoire de la dispersion du peuple du Manding, suite en Tape 10, Track A.
- "Niani Gouverneur", 1968; Tape 6; 1 (Box 6)
  Track A: A Farewell Speech in Niani, Guinea. Apparently on the occasion of the end of the second archeological season by the Polish expedition at Niani, speaker Mamadi Magasouba mentions the 1965 season, what Djibril Tamsir Niane was doing there for the past two months, ends with shouts of "Vive la Révolution, Vive Niane."
  Track A: Apparemment à l'occasion de la seconde saison archéologique par l'éxpédition Polonaise à Niani, l'informateur Mamadi Magasouba parle de la saison 1965, ce que Djibril Tamsir Niane avait fait là-bas durant les deux mois, et se termine avec des cris "Vive la Révolution, vive Niane"
- "Bagafo" [Bagata] "To Rèya-Alfa Yaya Les Professeurs", Circa 1969-1970; Tape 7; 1 (Box 7)
  Track A: Pular Language Oral Histories of Futa Jalon. Futa-Jalon elders speak to teachers and students of the University of Conakry; includes genealogy starting with Bodhewal of Boundou and reference to Koli Tenguela & Alpha Yaya Diallo.
  Track B: Baga village of Doupourou, Boffa region; replies to journalist's questions by Professors Shriver, Felix and Martin, with comment by Djibril Tamsir Niane.
  Scope and Contents
  Track A: Les anciens du Fouta-Djalon discutant avec les enseignants et les étudiants de l'Université de Conakry; incluant la généalogie de Bodhewal du Bondou et la référence de Koli Tenguela et Alpha Yaya Diallo.
  Track B: Le village Baga de Doupourou dans la région de Boffa; réponses des professeurs Shriver, Felix and Martin aux questions du journaliste, avec un commentaire de Djibril Tamsir Niane.
- "Mamaya Tènèngbè", Circa 1965-1970; Tape 8; 1 (Box 8)
  Track A: Orchestra Music. Radio broadcast of a Cuban band.
  Track B: A Tribute to Tènèngbè. Bala music by Sidi Madi accompanying speeches thanking a woman for her work with a Mamaya musical group that traveled to Côte d'Ivoire.
  Track A: Émission de radio d'un groupe [de musique] cubain.
  Track B: La musique bala jouée par Sidi Madi accompagnant des paroles remerciant une femme pour son travail avec son groupe Mamaya qui avait voyagé en Côte d'Ivoire.
- "Musique Orchestres", Circa 1965-1975; Tape 9; 1 (Box 9)
  Track B: Orchestra Music. Big Band sound, possibly Cuban.
  Track C: Dakar Radio Music. First fifteen minutes, Rock & Roll and R & B, blank space, ends with West African band.
  Track D: Dakar Radio Music. First four minutes, Latin, then pop mixture, Rock & Roll, R & B including Wilson Pickett, Ike & Tina Turner, James Brown, Santana, some Latino.
  Track E: Dakar Radio Music. Blank to five minutes, some West African big band, long blank space, ends with Latin.
  Track F: Dakar Radio Music. French R & B, Rock & Roll, some Latin.
  Track A: Émission de radio d'un groupe cubain.
  Track B: Son d'un Big band, peut-être cubain.
  Track C: Les quinze premières minutes Rock & Roll et R & B, blanc, se termine par un groupe d'Afrique de l'ouest.
  Track D: Les quatre premières minutes musique latino, puis unmélange pop, puis du Rock & Roll et R & B dont Wilson Pickett, Ike & Tina Turner, James Brown, Santana, et de la musique latino.
  Track E: Un blanc les cinq premières minutes, un big band d'Afrique de l'ouest, un long blanc, se finit avec de la misique latino.
  Track F: Le R & B, Rock & Roll français, musique latino.
- Kèlè Monson Diabaté recorded at Kita Geladio Diallo of Radio Mali (I), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 10; 1 (Box 10)
  Track A: Sunjata fasa Part 2, Kèlè Monson Diabaté. Continuing from Tape 5, Track A, traditional oral history of the settlement of Manden before the Mali Empire with genealogies of notable families.
  Track A: Suite de Tape 5, Track A, l'histoire de la tradition orale du peuplement du Mandé avant l'Empire du Mali avec les généalogies des familles de notables.
- Kèlè Monson Diabaté recorded at Kita Geladio Diallo of Radio Mali (II), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 11; 1 (Box 11)
  Track A: Sunjata fasa Part 3, Kèlè Monson Diabaté. Traditional oral history of the settlement of Manden before the Mali Empire with genealogies of notable families.
  Track A: L'histoire de la tradition orale de peuplement du Mandé avant l'Empire du Mali avec les généalogies des familles de notables.
- Kèlè Monson Diabaté recorded at Kita Geladio Diallo of Radio Mali (II) (continued), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 12; 1 (Box 12)
  Track A: Sunjata fasa Part 4, Kèlè Monson Diabaté. Early episodes of the Sunjata Epic.
  Track A: Les premiers épisodes de l'épopée de Soundiata.
- Kèlè Monson Diabaté recorded at Kita Geladio Diallo of Radio Mali (III), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 13; 1 (Box 13)
  Track A: Early episodes of the Sunjata epic.
- Kèlè Monson Diabaté recorded at Kita Geladio Diallo of Radio Mali (IV), Circa 1965-1975; Tape 14; 1 (Box 14)
  Track A: Sunjata fasa Part 5, Kèlè Monson Diabaté. Early episodes of the Sunjata epic.
- Baga Villages, History & Culture (I), Circa 1969-1970; Tape 15; 1 (Box 15)
  Approximately twenty minutes of a live Maninka language theater performance with very faint background guitar accompaniment, virtually indecipherable owing to crowd noise and bad recording quality.
  Circa vingt minutes d'enregistrement d'un pièce de théatre en maninka, avec en fond, accompagnement très faible à la guitare, pratiquement indéchiffrable a cause du bruit de la foule et de la mauvaise qualité d'enregistrement.
- Baga Villages, History & Culture (II), Circa 1969-1971; Tape 16; 1 (Box 16)
  Track A: Susu language interviews on the History & Culture of Baga Villages: Mintani and Monchon. 1. Three Baga Forè masks, early settlers and woodcarvers 2. The sacred table Andisa and musical instruments 3. Genealogy of first nine generations of Camara in Monchon; Fouta Jalon battle of Taransan, masks including Monsèdi (Baga a-Tshol); includes lines in Baga Foré dialect.
  Track A: 1. Trois masques Baga Foré, des anciens habitants et des sculpteurs sur bois; 2. Andisa la table sacrée et les instruments de musique; 3. Généalogie des neuf premières générations des Camara à Monchon; la bataille de Fouta Djalon à Taransan, les masques incluant Monsèdi (Baga a-Tshol); comprend des lignes du dialecte Baga Foré.
- Baga Villages, History & Culture (III), Circa 1969-1970; Tape 17; 1 (Box 17)
  Track A: Susu language Interviews on the History & Culture of Baga Villages: Kamsar and Yongonsal. 1. Mamadou Camara on the arrival of earliest Baga peoples; 2. Woodcarvers & their villages; 3. Elhadj Idrissa woodcarvers, masks, and early Baga islanders.
  Track A: 1. Mamadou Camara, au sujet de l'arrivées des plus anciens peuples Baga; 2. Les sculpteurs sur bois et leurs villages; 3. Elhadj Idrissa, les sculpteurs, les masques et les premiers insulaires baga.
- "Radiodiffusion du Senegal", Circa 1969-1970; Tape 18; 1 (Box 18)
  Track A: Two Songs from Baga-land. 1. A wedding song in the Mikiforé language; 2. Chorus in Baga-Pukur language with siko drum and calabash rattles.
  Track A: 1. Une chanson de marriage en mikiforé; 2. Un choeur en baga pukur avec un tambour siko et des calebasses.
- "Doyen Niani 1968 Nansirimamba", Tape 19; 1 (Box 19)
  Track A: Djibril Tamsir Niane Interview at Niani with Mamadouba Keita. Maninka history of Niani by a Keita, not a jeli (professional bard), beginning with ancestor Nansirimamba, founding of the village of Makònò, war with the Kado (Dogon) of Kétankoro, reference to Kunjan as mansa of the Konyanka, founding of Niani by the sons of Nanfin Mori, a.k.a. Balama Mori Keita.
  Track A: Entretien en malinké sur l'histoire de Niani par un Keita qui n'est pas jeli, commençant par l'ancêtre Nansirimamba, fondation du village de Makònò, la guerre avec les Kado (Dogon) de Kétankoro, se référant à Kunjan comme mansa de Konyanka, la fondation de Niani par Nanfin Mori dit Balama Mori Keita.
- "Doyen de Niani 1968", Tape 20; 1 (Box 20)
  Track A: Continuation of Tape 19, Track A, Djibril Tamsir Niane Interview at Niani with Mamadouba Keita. Maninka history of the founding of Niani, variant of episodes of the Sunjata Epic with Fakoli, claims Sunjata settled at Niani after the war with Sosso.
  Track A: Histoire Malinké sur la fondation de Niani, variant sur les épisodes de l'épopée de Soundjata avec Fakoli, prétend que Soundjata s'est installé à Niani après la guerre avec les Sosso.
- "Niani 1968 Histoire Musique Village Bugo", Circa 1965-1970; Tape 21; 1 (Box 21)
  Track A: Welcome to Siguiri. About three minutes of jenbe music with male voice accompanied by ngarinya (iron rasp) and female voice, welcoming somebody to the town of Siguiri.
  Track A: Les trois premières minutes de la musique jenbe avec une voix masculine accompagnée par un ngarinya (instrument métalique) et une voix féminine, souhaitant la bienvenue à quelqu'un dans la ville de Siguiri.
- "Niani 1968 Kimeni Kono Mousso", 1969; Tape 22; 1 (Box 22)
  Track A: Pular Language Oral Histories of the Futa-Jalon. Conflict between leaders including Boubacar Biro; a story of Al-Hadj 'Umar; pre-Fula inhabitants; Mande invasion by Brahima Condé.
  Track A: Conflit entre les leaders incluant Boubacar Biro; une histoire d'El-Hadj Oumar; les premiers habitants peuls; l'invasion des Mandé par Brahima Condé.
- "Niani 1968 Chant Karite", Tape 23; 1 (Box 23)
  Track A: Maninka Women's Music at Niani, Guinea. Djibril Tamsil Niane converses with Jelimuso Tata who studied with Jeli Musa Kaba, talks about her profession and sings in a beautiful soprano voice, beginning with the song "Eh Nawa;" interrupted by about 5 minutes of female music, then the interview continues to the end.
  Track A: Djibril Tamsil Niane conversant avec Jelimuso Tata qui a étudié avec Jeli Musa Kaba, elle parle de sa profession et chante avec une belle voix mélodieuse, commençant avec la chanson "Eh Nawa;" interrompu par cinq minutes de musique féminine, ensuite l'entretien reprend jusqu'à la fin.
- "Wasulu Musique Tradition Poésie Création", Circa 1968-1969; Tape 24; 1 (Box 24)
  Track A: Traditional Maninka Music. A jelimuso sings to jenbe music with female chorus; sudden change to hunters' singer with a Senufo accent accompanied by ngaryinya and flute, songs "Filèké and Miniyamba".
  Track A: Une jelimuso chante avec la musique jenbe et des choristes; soudain change avec un chasseur chantant avec un accent Sénoufo accompagné par un ngarinya et une flûte, le titre de la chanson "Filèké et Miniyamba".
- Tamsir Niane, Circa 1969-1971; Tape 25; 1 (Box 25)
  Track A: The Story of Djanka Wali. Mikiforé language, Maran Dabo tells the story of Djanka Wali's progress from Kaabu to Futa Jalon, with reference to Alpha Yaya Diallo.
  Track A: La langue Mikiforé, Maran Dabo raconte l'histoire du progrès de Djanka Wali du Kaabu au Fouta-Djalon, avec la référence de Alpha Yaya Diallo.
- "Wasulu 3 Sept. 1972", Tape 26; 1 (Box 26)
  Track A: Songs in Praise of President Sékou Touré of Guinea. Two Guinean orchestras praise the president in the Maninka language.
  Track B: Thanks to Sékou Touré. Ten seconds of Fulfulde female chorus singing "thanks" to President Sékou Touré of Guinea, remainder of the tape is blank.
  Track A: Deux orchestres guinéens font les louanges du président en malinké.
  Track B: Dix secondes des choristes chantant en peul pour remercier le président Sékou Touré de Guinée, le reste de la bande est vide.
- "Nouveautés du Disque No. 152", Circa 1970-1975; Tape 27; 1 (Box 27)
  Track A: Part 1, Sunjata fasa (An episode of the Sunjata epic) by Mori Kanté. A live concert in honor of Djibril Tamsir Niane, narration and vocals by Mori Kanté with bala music by Kèlètigi Diabaté, guitar by Jelimani Tounkara.
  Track A: Concert live en honneur de Djibril Tamsir Niane, raconté et chanté par Mori Kanté avec la musique bala par Kélétigui Diabaté, à la guitare Jelimani Tounkara.
- "Histoire", 1966; Tape 28; 1 (Box 28)
  Track A: Part 2 of an interview in Segou, Mali with a Veteran of Sekou Amadou's Campaign to Sokoto. Bamana language, begun on Tape 1, Track A, recorded over an earlier interview in the Wolof language but some sentences are partially decipherable, naming towns including Kano, with a few details about circumstances of battle.
  Track B: Part 3 of an interview in Segou, Mali with a Veteran of Sekou Amadou's Campaign to Sokoto. Bamana language, begun on booo1a, recorded over an earlier recording and in present condition this is as, indecipherable as Tape 1, Track A.
  Track C: [indecipherable audio recording]
  Track A: La langue bambara qui avait commencé en Tape 1, Track A, l'enregistrement couvre un ancien morceau en langue wolof, mais quelques phrases sont partiellement déchiffrables, nommant les villes incluant Kano, avec peu de détails concernant les circonstances des guerres.
  Track B: La langue bambara qui avait commencé en Tape 1, Track A, l'enregistrement couvre un ancien morceau, et est déchiffrable dans les conditions actuelles.
  Track C: [entièrement déchiffrable]
- Djibril Tamsir Niane Interviews an Informant at Niani, Guinea, 1968; Tape 29; 1 (Box 29)
  Track A: Dutigi (Chief) Moriba Keita introduces Diabakun Condé who replies to Niane's questions about history of Niani.
  Le chef (dutigi) Moriba Keita introduisant Diabakun Condé qui répondait aux questions de Niane sur l'histoire de Niani.
- "Samory", Circa 1965-1975; Tape 30; 1 (Box 30)
  Track A: The Epic of Almami Samori Touré. Continuation of Tape 3, Track A, epic of Samori; his war against Makhan Famudu of Wasulu.
  Track A: La suite de Tape 3, Track A, l'épopée de Samori; sa guerre contre Makhan Famudu du Wasulu.
- International Colloquium on the Oral Traditions of Kaabu (Present-day Guinea-Bissau), 1980 May 19-1980 May 24; Tape 31; 1 (Box 31)
  Track A: International Colloquium on the Oral Traditions of Kaabu (Present-day Guinea-Bissau) at the Fondation Léopold Sédar Senghor in Dakar, Senegal. French language radio broadcast from Dakar with participants from the United State., France, the United Kingdom, Gambia, Mali, Guinea, etc., including Djibril Tamsir Niane and Sèkènè Mody Sissoko.
  Track A: Émission radio en français à Dakar, avec des participants venus des U.S.A., France, U.K., Gambie, Mali, Guinée, etc., incluant Djibril Tamsir Niane et Sékéné Mody Sissoko.
- "Musique", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 32; 1 (Box 32)
  Track A: Part 2, Sunjata fasa (an episode of the Sunjata Epic) by Mori Kanté. Live concert in honor of Djibril Tamsir Niane continued from Tape 27, Track A, the Jolofin Mansa episode.
  Track B: Léopold Sédar Senghor, President of Senegal. A French language radio interview, followed by unrelated other broadcasts.
  Track A: Concert live en honneur de Djibril Tamsir Niane, la suite de Tape 27, Track A, l'épisode de Jolofin Mansa.
  Track B: Entretien à la radio en français, suivi par d'autres émissions.
- "Tam-Tam et Danse Folklorique", Circa 1970-1975; Tape 33; 1 (Box 33)
  Track A: Traditional Maninka Music and a discussion of marriage. Jenbe music and children's song 7:20; interview with a woman and men, including Djibril Tamsir Niane joking about wanting to marry her daughter 16:00, blank to 32:00; more jenbe with jelimusow singing.
  Track A: La musique jenbe avec le chant des enfants en 7:20; entretien avec une femme et des hommes, incluant Djibril Tamsir Niane, disant, pour plaisante, qu'il veut épouser sa fille; de 16:00 à 32:00 espace vide; plus de jenbe avec des chants de jelimuso.
- "Conte et Musique 20", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 34; 1 (Box 34)
  Track A: Traditional Music and French Language Radio Drama. Kora music with a Maninka male vocalist to 17:35; French broadcast of Jouons la Comédie by Nestor Zensou and brief interview with Stanislas Abovi.
  Track A: La musique kora avec une voix masculine en malinké en 17:35; émission en français de Jouons la Comédie par Nestor Zensou et un entretien bref avec Stanislas Abovi.
- "L'histoire du President Léopold Senghor du Senegal 22", Circa 1970-1979; Tape 35; 1 (Box 35)
  Track A: Léopold Sédar Senghor, President of Senegal. A French language radio interview broadcast in Dakar, Senegal.
  Track A: Émission en français de la radio de Dakar, Sénégal.
- "L'histoire Mamoudou 4 Maninka", Circa 1965-1975; Tape 36; 1 (Box 36)